hello and welcome
it's March 17 2023 we're here in active
live stream number 53.0
welcome to the active Institute we're a
participatory online Institute that is
communicating learning and practicing
applied active inference you can find us
at the links on the slide
this is a recorded and archived live
stream so please provide feedback so we
can improve our work all backgrounds and
perspectives are welcome we'll be
following video etiquette for live
streams
head over to
activeinference.org to learn more about
the Institute and getting involved with
learning groups and projects
we're here in active stream number 53.0
and our goal is to learn and discuss a
pair of papers
the first paper is snakes and ladders in
paleoanthropology from cognitive
surprise to skillfulness a million years
ago
by Hector manrique Carl friston and
Michael Walker
the article was posted to Psy archive in
and the second paper is to copy or not
to copy that is the question
from chimpanzees to the foundation of
human technological culture
this paper is with manrique and Walker
as authors fristinless
it was also uploaded to Psy archive and
recently as we have been delighted to
discover
the paper has been accepted in physics
of Life reviews however the quotes that
we're drawing from and reading from
today
are drawn from the psy archive version
just so people know
and like all the videos
we're here to make an introduction for
some of the ideas and the materials it's
not a review or a final word
in this 53.0 video we're going to
introduce ourselves say hello and then
we are going to call it like we see it
with the aims and claims abstract
roadmap keywords and there are no
figures or formalisms in these papers
but I think we'll have enough bounded
surprise to navigate nonetheless so let
us begin with introductions and then
we'll head into big questions so Dean
thanks darling I'm Dean I'm here in
Calgary uh I'm not going to do much
around the warm-up question piece
because I've got a big question coming
up
so I'll pass it over to you
I'm Daniel I'm in California and agreed
please lead in with your big questions
well I'm going to start by uh just sort
of
highlighting that the big questions that
the authors have if that's okay I'll
just read them out
um so for the Snakes and Ladder paper uh
there were a number of questions that uh
sort of enabled the the authors to to go
forward with their ideas two questions
arise first what is it that could
provoke cognitive awareness as to the
possibility of fashioning stone hand
axes in relation to the affordances of
raw materials and potential advantages
for minimizing bioenergetic effort
secondly what does this say about the
irregular appearance
of this regular technique in the
pleistocene spatial Temple record
also how was remembered awareness
retrieved from personal short and
long-term memory transmitted as
knowledge
two others in whose memories it could
become embedded with a degree of
fidelity sufficient to enable
intergenerational or intercommunal
diffusion how far was observational
learning involved do you want me to read
the um crnc or or do you want to do that
yourself all right I'll read the
questions from the authors in copy or
not to copy they wrote why do
chimpanzees not live in a world not live
in a complex technological world
why does innovation fail to translate
into technological cumulative complexity
does it owe to a limited capacity to
copy with fidelity
what is the implication for Innovations
what ingredients must be present from a
free energy principle standpoint in
innovators Minds
slash brains and in observers mind slash
brains for Innovation to take root in a
community and be transmitted between
Generations
yeah great questions
now
how do we want well we know how where we
want to do this but one of the things
before we get too far along is uh
we want to we as as hosts today really
want to honor the fact that a lot of
time has been spent making sure that um
be
ideas that the authors want to bring
into the public domain are very
clear and that we don't read a whole
bunch into it now
we're not going to speculate we're not
going to go off on any kind of tangent
here we're going to try to focus
strictly on the arguments that they are
putting forward because they're putting
forward some pretty
um strong and I think well evidenced
arguments so although there's lots of
questions being asked they're also
trying to provide a few very defendable
answers
absolutely
that is to Prelude the questions that we
Dean and I and Ali are asking and then
we're going to dive largely into
verbatim quotations from the texts and
we'll have a dessert
session where we bring up some future
topics and ideas
what big question brought you into this
53d okay so apologies there can be a lot
of reading today so if you don't like my
voice you're gonna just read this and
hit the pause button but anyway the
attention to Optical transition as paper
one to paper two and we're not really
spending a lot of time right now saying
which came first because we we think of
them as a pair
uh the ship between Snakes and Ladders
model of evolution and learning
comparisons across species with special
tension given to Innovation as copying
ability both paper there is much to say
and discuss around learning is an uptake
exercise
if as reviewers people reading these
papers we were to taken active and then
in between that and inference
Anthropologist archaeologist comparative
psychologist approach
to combining these manuscripts and then
I singled out many examples of where the
authors speak expressively around
combining combinatorial and you can read
that on your own if we were to look at
combinations what might we learn when
bicameral for example two eyes and
bi-temporal meaning holding up then and
now strategies as analysis are
approximated with active in inference as
parentheses to uptake for example
telescopes and microscope usage after
before or concurrent
with compounding strategy uptake
so that's my big question and I think
we're probably not going to get close to
an answer until the dot two that's why
it's a big question because I think it's
going to be able to span
a little bit of a window here
great and I wrote a shorter question
apart from other applications for
example in research and development or
in other fields or looking towards the
future
how does the free energy principle and
active inference serve as a historical
framework or approach so whether we lean
towards Aristotelian causation
philosophies or ten Bergen's approach to
ethology behavioral analysis
how does a historical explanatory power
fit in amongst the wise the plurality of
wise
in our investigations and Ali who is
joining for some discussions proposed
the question how can self-organized
systems use copy discard functions to
store information
a little bit of an externalization from
our category Theory developments that
I'm sure will arise later
so
you go for the top I'll go for the
bottom
okay so just before I start I want to I
want to really
emphasize the fact that the authors
um I think to really comprehend what the
authors are trying to
put forward as an idea here you have to
really spend some time thinking through
the aims of the papers and the claims we
placed a heavy emphasis we're going to
give a lot more time over that it's
going to seem like we're going to give a
lot of time over to the keys because uh
having talked to the authors prior to
coming on and doing this live stream set
they use those terms of the key and the
key to unlocking some of these IDs that
have been held for a long time so
apologies again if it seems like we're
text heavy or dialogue heavy but in
order to really appreciate what's going
on you have to kind of get it out there
so for the snakes and lattice paper
provide a hypothesis
a paradigmatic account around how
variational free energy is both
individual onto genetic and Collective
phylogenetic modeling
could have played a part in What could
now be described as a methodological
epip fpp Paradigm or relating biological
and technological behavior in homo
snakes and ladders in this context
pertains to
appearances and disappearances of
Paleolithic skills in the early and
middle pleistocene record
our proposal in books and methodological
Paradigm grounded
in existential principles that underpin
the evolution of living organisms it is
that some at least of The Irregular
regularities
and regular irregularities of phenomena
attributable to homo in the pleistocene
record reflect the kinds of plausibility
anomalous behavioral outcomes that
doubtless occurred often in a stakes and
Ladder model of evolution in early
members of our genus regardless of their
skeletal paleo-specific taxonomy
awesome I'll read the bottom and then
feel free to
explain the side by side visually
they wrote into copy or not to copy
an aim is to introduce the notion that
chimpanzees and other great apes show
considerable limitations in their
ability or Zone a bounded surprisal to
overcome cognitive surprisal induced by
Innovative or unorthodox Behavior which
is rarely rarely is copied precisely or
accurately so things that can be
innovated
in a moment but do not have the ability
to be recognized and carried forward
and they discuss the circumstances under
which pleistocene homo underwent
remarkable evolutionary adaptation of
neurobiological propensities
cerebral aspects are discussed that it
is proposed here
were fundamental for faithful copying
Which underpins social transmission of
Technology's cumulative culture and
culture
so I think what we're going to be doing
is holding up two things at once the two
things are copying as repetition and
copying as origination if there is such
a word but essentially these images here
there are copies that were simply cut
and pasted so they were repeated and
then there was one representation
between those two that's an origination
it didn't exist to be copied but now it
can be
so now what we're going to be doing is
looking at Okay so
how does maybe all of that
play out when we're observing the world
around us when we're taking things in
and trying to reduce our surprise how
many things are we being faked on how
many things are actually original
representational and therefore
manageable as as two very different
places of of
understanding or appreciation Maybe
great all right I'll go for the first of
the sections and then feel free to
comment on them or to pick up on the
second sections okay so in Snakes and
Ladders they wrote
cognitive surprises favoring anomalous
behavioral propensities to sporadic
expression can explain Snakes and
Ladders appearances and disappearances
of Paleolithic skills in the early and
middle pleistocene record
some behavioral outcomes attributable
plausibly to individual members of homo
unable to maintain Orthodox behavioral
responses when faced with cognitive
surprises which is surprisal in the
Bayesian terminology
such individuals may show a particular
neurobiological propensity for exploring
unorthodox possibilities the propensity
has evolved further in humans than in
great apes which unlike even our very
young children are larva
seem unable to envisage how things might
be as well as how they actually are
whereas by coupling recall of past
experience with prospective memory
humans are capable of blending reality
among different potential spheres
statistical considerations of classical
population genetics are in commensurate
with
Notions the darwinian fitness and
pleistocene Homo increased imperceptibly
through gradual dual inheritance
coevolution
inherited changes proceeded in
well-night invariant lockstep with
heritability of adaptive behavioral and
technological changes although onto
genetic autopoiesis may involve action
perception Cycles a phylogenetic
consequence could include unawareness by
companions that those exceptions might
allow new Cooperative opportunities for
minimizing the group's variation free
energy by performing unaccustomed
Behavior to attain dubious benefit
the four-sided fluent communication
Innovations often must have disappeared
unremarkable
seen as useless and their Creator's
prowesses misplaced energy and wasting
time needed for satisfying the group's
existentially implacable energetics
free potent routine behavior and
pro-social early homo plausibly resulted
in Failure to become aware of the
potential of idiosyncratic inactive
outcomes
here a prosaic approach
merely inverts that Narrative Approach
to interpreting the Deep past which
draws for its inspiration on Humane and
social studies
the inversion subordinates
The Narrative Approach to critical
scrutiny such that The Narrative
Approach no longer seems to be the most
appropriate or most parsimonious
interpretation available now again what
we're doing is trying to avoid the
situation where we're cherry picking so
if you want to pause and read what's
been written in context please feel free
to do that but we just want to make sure
that we touch on the you know the
highest peaks in this range
yes the full papers are out there
were linearizing and curating in this
dot zero which has been
incredible experience and that has
helped us
grasp some of these points
hopefully so we can take them further
and I'll read the quote and then you can
go into the Red Zone yeah go for it in
Snakes and Ladders they wrote
the argument proposed here
about a neurobiological propensity to an
individual enactment in modifying Stone
considered from the standpoint of the
free energy principle
is not concerned with a null hypothesis
of innate latent spontaneity
instead it is directed towards
interpreting irregular regularities and
regular irregularities in the
pleistocene snakes and ladders record of
appearances and disappearances of BF
lcts which we're going to get to tools
given presence of BF lcts in widely
differing biotopes which likely led to
differential behavioral evolution of
appropriate subsistence strategies and
diets there is widespread comparability
of the principal morphological
attributes of BF lcts of diverse
petrology at sites with contrasting
paleo environments and different
spatio-temporal contexts or
paleoanthropological tax
this renders unlikely any notion of a
straightforward mendelian genetic basis
favoring BF LCT outcomes by natural
selection for a specific behavioral
adaptation
the circumstantial evidence seems to
apply the Adaptive evolution of human
neurobiology propensities that support
prospective memory in tool making
together with short-term working memory
including haptic working memory
long-term working memory and long-term
procedural memory and episodic memory of
past matters and things
so I just wanted I'm doing a tease here
because on the previous slide I starred
one of the claims and then the last
claim on this blide here my note was
essentially I'm just going to read the
part that
doesn't again have me speculating memory
broken into types as you can see here
working memory long-term procedural Etc
and now being applied instrumentally did
all the memory types at some threshold
of uptake afford a parallel processing
of time given times potential variance
over the simpler sequential sense of
change as the starter pack priority
today
and when I say started by priority today
how much about what we do today is being
projected or over fit onto the Deep past
this is a question that Michael's
presentation in the 53.1 is going to
have much to say uh also the last claim
of the cop you're not to copy so a bit a
bit of a teaser you're going to want to
show up for 53.1 because I think
Michael's presentation is going to
really open up a lot of eyes
awesome
into to copy or not to copy we go to
their claims so just to read some of the
first parts
what is the implication for Innovations
acina quinone
for one to spread so something that must
happen to spread is following its
conception by one mind namely the hmm
hierarchically mechanistic mind of the
protagonist brain it must then be
apprehended by another mind namely the
hmm of an observer's brain and we're
going to come back to that on the
roadmap
here Innovations represent an anomaly
and innovators are unorthodox actors or
protagonists
their policy selection is in a sense
faulty
in the sense that they're ensuring
behavioral outcomes are in Market
contrast to those with their fellow
actors or agents who deploy Orthodox
responses
that reduce discrepancies between
predictions and sensation
thus innovators fail to fulfill their
predictions if Innovations be regarded
as behavioral outputs
theirs are then responses that fall
outside the repertoire typical of their
community
and hence Seterus paribus all of the
things equal increase the prediction
error EG the level of cognitive
surprisal in
their exchanges with the surrounding Eco
niche
predicted consequences of any observed
Innovative Behavior will be too
imprecise for the cons specific to make
sense of that novel or unorthodox
Behavior
when sins cannot be made copying cannot
take place
very clear
when can brains when brains cope with
high levels of cognitive surprisles a
plausible answer is that it is when the
holding capacity of working memory
increases from two to three working
memory in this setting corresponds to
the temporal depth
of generative models that generate or
predict the consequences of successive
actions this transition increases
temporal Horizon which amplifies
cognitive versatility and
one of my favorite things recursive
thinking
a working memory or d-temper model able
to entertain diverse novel Bayesian
beliefs is more likely able to recognize
and remember Innovative behaviors
and
it's easier for chimpanzees to perform
complex actions that involve
considerable motor demands
than it is for them to reproduce actions
they're simple and undemanding with
regard to motor dexterity and yet
unorthodox with regard to their habitual
behavioral repertoire
great all just
just joking meme internally as we carry
forward
oh yeah go for the top half here all
right I'll do the first three when
considering early please just
pleistocene Behavior we need not assume
memories were less complex like psycho
cognitively
than ours it is prosaically sufficient
to infer that they were simply less
frequent
owing to earlier consolidation of
cerebral networks and Homo erectus's
smaller brain
and we're going to get into think
something called The Zone abounded
surprisal here and after the zbs
restricted them
observations by early Homo erectus were
translated often into activity
intermediate between
I love that emulation and imitation
owing to limited foresight
that or their zbs limited their ability
to join up the mental steps involved in
planning and to infer counterfactual
possibilities the focus of the zbs is on
The Observers and their ability to make
sense of an observed innovation
the zps allows any potentially novel or
unorthodox Behavior to be copied
provided that
the ranges or the levels of surprise
provoked in observers are tolerated or
manageable by
there's bilateral neuronal activation in
some brain regions when some tools are
being fashioned
activation is bilateral because
fastening Stone requires precise and
accurate monitoring by right hemisphere
neurons of the left hand holding the
future artifact as well as the actions
shaping it performed by the right hand
holding a hammer Stone which are
monitored by left hemisphere neurons
together they coordinate continuously
changing sensory motor representations
with appropriately changing hand
movements undertaken in an organized
forward sequence of perception action
with feedback
entertaining multiple and varied
predictions
in the Bayesian framework represented as
probability densities
in alternate models generated about
reality
enables the narrowing of cognitive gaps
or lessening of cognitive dissonance or
surprisal when con specifics are seen to
carry out unusual or unorthodox
behaviors
that paves the way for horizontal and
vertical transmission
the working memory capacity of
chimpanzees seems to be below that
tipping point at which multiple mental
spheres or possibilities can be
entertained simultaneously for pitting
against an observed novel Behavior while
keeping cognitive surprisal within a
tolerable range
unsurprisingly no copying occurs when
Innovations observed
deviate markedly from usual chimpanzee
behaviors
can I just throw something in here now
at this point just we'll step back and
think about this as a live stream we are
trying to avoid a Tipping Point by
placing a heavy weighting on the aims
and claims relative to most of the live
streams that we've done in the past this
is a big build up but think of this as
your classic barbell
um analogy we've just set one plate on
the bar now we're going to look at the
bar and then we're going to look at the
other plates on the other side of this
when we get to the Keys
you can go for the first abstract I'll
do the second you got it okay a
scientific paradigmatic accounts vices
to interpret behavioral evolution in
nearly homo cognitive surprises favoring
anomalous behavioral propensities to
sporadic expression and explain stakes
and ladders appearances and
disappearances of Paleolithic skills in
the early middle pleistine record
the account applies to the principle of
stationary action which underpins the
free energy principle
to self-organizing systems at an
evolutionary time scale unusual personal
attainments
often explained by invoking Progressive
Ascent of evolutionary phylogenetic
ladders of cognitive and Technical
abilities could be disregarded in a
hominin community that failed to imagine
or articulate possible advantages for
its survivability such failure as well
as diverse fortuitous demographic
accidents could erase from Collective
memory the recollection of exceptional
individual conduct which disappeared
down a snake so to speak of the human
evolutionary public
puzzle discomforts paleoanthropologists
the gloves are on
um some explain it away with the
self-justifying assertion that separate
Payless species of homo differentially
possessed cognitive abilities that
allegedly underlay the differential
presence or absence in the pleistocene
archaeological record of traces a
particular behavioral outcomes or skills
an alternative methodological
perspective grounded in the fundamental
relationships between organisms of their
environments of forwards parsimonious
prosaic deflationary account for
appearances and disappearances of
Behavioral outcomes and skills thus the
title Snakes and Ladders
great and the abstract of copy or not to
copy
the prerequisite for copying Innovative
behavior is the capacity of observers
brains regarded as hierarchically
mechanistic Minds to overcome cognitive
surprisal by maximizing the evidence for
their internal models via active
inference
unlike modern humans chimpanzees and
other great apes show considerable
limitations in their ability or zone of
bounded surprisal to overcome cognitive
surprisal induced by Innovative or
unorthodox Behavior which rarely is
copied precisely or accurately most can
copy adequately what is within their
phenotypically habitual behavioral reper
in which technology plays A scant Part
widespread intra and intergenerational
social transmission of complex
technological innovations is not a
Hallmark of gray ape taxa
over 3 million years ago precursors of
the genus homo made Stone artifacts and
stone flaking was likely habitual before
2 million years ago
after this time early Homo erectus left
traces of technological innovations
though faithful copying of these and
their intra and intergenerational social
transmission were rare before a million
years ago
this likely owed to a cerebral
infrastructure of intercorrect connected
neuronal networks that bounds the
expressivity of internal World models
entailed by their functional
architecture
brains were smaller in size than ours
and cerebral neuronal networks cease to
develop when early Homo erectus attain
full adult maturity by the mid-teen
years
whereas their development continues
until our mid-20s nowadays
pleistocene homo underwent remarkable
evolutionary adaptation of
neurobiological propensities cerebral
aspects are discussed that it is
proposed here
were fundamental for faithful copying
Which underpins social transmission of
Technologies cumulative learning and
culture
great
one of the most amazing road map became
Road rail became
train station Clearinghouse slides so
what is happening
so
the the I think the great gift that the
authors have provided Daniel and I here
is the opportunity because this this
work is talking about sequential time
and when on that timeline did things
happen which came first
or why did something that we thought
came after suddenly we find new evidence
that maybe it didn't come after maybe it
was co-occurring and so what I wanted to
do in this particular slide was talk
about things like timelines and
timetables
around the idea of a learning
destination assuming
that learning does have some
sense of
convergence so my question was well what
if all roads be it be the rail or paved
lead to an active room or room fronts
like what is this journey that we're on
what is this interstate that we exist
within and why do we always assume that
what we're looking at is the ties
between the rails instead of making sure
that when we're talking about a Tipping
Point we're talking about the fact that
the entire underlying structure can hold
up the vehicle that Daniel and I are are
basically sitting on right now and
moving forward with back and forth so
the timelines and timetables to learning
destinations are not uptakes someone
else's formatting is not your outing of
a figure okay so I've never I've never
been on an official dig site but I have
come across uh dinosaur bones being in
Alberta and so you stumble across these
things and whoa what's that right and in
otherwise field of play how much can we
schedule and how much is dependent on
the sophistication of our hierarchical
model and again I've practiced this to
strenues to train is
with apologies to Hector
where are we departing all we know is
it's that's uh platforms one and nine
let's go
vamos All Aboard but great great
visualization the papers do have
sections however without figures or
formalisms
we were able to and drawing on the
unique subject matter and contributions
able to also even reconsider the
linearity and the structure of the
Stream
the keywords are displayed on the slide
just to quickly read through them in
Snakes and Ladders free energy principle
fep
Paleolithic enactment irregular
regularities and regular irregularities
haptic working memory tasks prospective
epistotic and procedural memory
phylogenetic and autogenetic time skills
favoring anomalous behavioral
propensities to sporadic expression
the principle of stationary action
applied to self-organizing systems at an
evolutionary time scale and in copier
not to copy chimpanzees cumulative
culture free energy principle generative
model Homo erectus Innovation Observer
stone tools technology and the zones of
bounded surprisal
what can you add about the published
priors
well I just think it's interesting
because we've always used this uh this
image of the sort of the infinite and
uh
ant Prince ref which I've always really
liked because
um I just momentarily lost the uh
the strange loot piece what is that
Mobius is it a Mobius right
a Mobius strip also developed by here
M.C Escher and Doug hofstetter into the
strange Loop concept right right so all
I wanted to do was add that the fact
that maybe maybe there is these um
Branch lines
and when we're talking about published
priors which can like I mean no they I
know that in in the chronological time
they came first but if we were now to go
to them post having read these papers
what what would that reveal right like
it's a branch less important than the
trunk I guess I don't know without a
trunk there are no branches but without
branches there aren't there is no
there's no totality so that's what I was
kind of laying out there
also with respect to the literature
it's a canonical example of cumulative
culture it's all at once
and the timing of which through Kronos
Publications were added in
is by no means the Kronos or the Kairos
of the learner or the researcher so
going from just the past and the present
to Min 2 of the literature to the past
present and future
three with literature
expanse
into the key points with another uh
disclaimer for your health
there are no calls notes version it will
both make sense and do justice the
analysis research arguments is laid out
in these papers
we begin with keys and then start a
process of unlocking all right so
how do you want to do this Daniel you
want to split the each one of the slides
or do you want to just swap slides I'll
do one you do one yep you go for this
slide you go for even slides I'll do odd
slides okay all right so this is all the
keys there are 17 of them from the
snakes in the ladder paper
again I really strongly recommend you
have a read of this it's a fantastic
paper
but if you want the um one and a half
times speed version of hearing it this
is what it sounds like evidence of early
middle pleistocene behavior is
distributed in disconcertingly uneven
ways between 2 million and 200 000 years
ago our proposal is that some at least
of The Irregular regularies and regular
irregularities a phenomena attributable
attributable to homo in the pleistocene
record reflect the kinds a plausibly
anomalous behavioral outcomes that
doubtless occurred often in a stakes and
ladders model of evolution in early
members of our genus regardless of their
skeletal paleo-specific taxonomy
increasingly complex extractive and
concomitant or consequent procedures
appear in several parts of the world at
various times towards the end of the
late pleistocene some seem to have
Arisen separately and independently in a
snakes and ladders fashion and with
different outcome in different places
and times
self-evidising underwrites much of the
following arguments however there is an
important nuance
certain creatures may have evolved deep
generative models with the ability to
predict the consequences of their
actions this kind of creature now has
the capacity to entertain counterfactual
Futures under different actions
this is a key aspect of active inference
under the fpp namely actions and plans
are selected on the basis of minimizing
expected free energy under that plan
in terms of Bayesian mechanics Evolution
and natural selection can be regarded as
natural Bayesian model selection which
is also known as structure learning in
the cognitive Sciences Evolution thus
develops imperceptibly and
intermittently and the fep concept is
biologically and especially
neurobiologically relevant both at onto
genetic levels of cellular Dynamics
neural circuitry and behavior and that
follow the genetic levels of populations
evolve through natural selection of
biological adaptations and adaptability
just before we move on because there's
much other Keys here
I hope it makes sense that not only are
we setting the bars up or the plates up
on either end of the bar
if we're talking about a Tipping Point
we as the agent who are going to now
bring that bar down to our chest and
then re-extend ourselves we don't want
the Tipping Point to be the bar comes
down and then squishes us
so uh setting this up there's a there's
not a Tipping Point as a threshold is
met and over the whole thing goes the
Tipping Point is here
is there is there some agent that's
actually capable of
we're talking directly about them
continuing with snakes and ladders
doubtless tried and trusted routines
predominated and whoever performed them
with daily efficiency was trusted by the
group whereas eccentric or idiosyncratic
conduct was treated with indifference
and not retained in Collective memory or
lore
pre-potent routine Behavior
plausibly resulted in Failure to become
aware of potentially idiosyncratic and
active outcomes
there is a difference between a spatio
temporal Snakes and Ladders picture of
disappearances of tiny hunter-gatherer
bands and appearances of others
and the snakes and ladders model of
individual idiosyncratic or unorthodox
activity
heterogeneous composition renders the
former picture inappropriate for making
predictions
whereas the latter model
individual idiosyncratic or unorthodox
activity
by focusing on the information theoretic
and energetic constraints on biological
neurobiological and psychosocial
Evolution allows for the consideration
of whether by doing so it may offer a
reasonable interpretation of the
material record in particular the uneven
distribution of stone hand axes and
evidence of Paleolithic combustion
between 2 million and 200 000 years ago
the marginal relevance of stone about
three million years ago for the
existential biological imperative of
maintaining homeostatic integrity and
consequent reproductive success and
survival of inarticulate hominina
plausibly LED stones to be regarded as
quintessentially predictable and
unsurprising and crucially lacking
epistemic affordances implicit in tool
use
nevertheless an individual could
entertain more expressive I.E deeper
generative models and respond to
exploratory epistemic and exploitative
pragmatic value
she might discover novel ways of
attaining predictable or unsurprising
outcomes through her behavior and its
outcome May well have been disregarded
by her companions
all the same
such idiosyncratic Behavior made Trump
prevailing expectations that normally
are unsurprising and therefore favor
minimization of variational free energy
in line with the free energy principle
it is unclear by what mechanism
transmission of any conjectural package
could have been sustained over the
spatiotemporal dimensions involved
and so with respect to some kinds of
tool usage it is improved to infer that
they reflect an unbroken tradition of
manual Behavior handed down from
generation to generation
if a generation lasts 25 years on
average then 200 000 years imply eight
thousand Generations which presents a
major challenge for the culture history
approach to interpretation
BF lcts were made by precursors of H
sapiens in Africa
and Neanderthals in Europe probably both
used in similar ways nevertheless the
uneven spatial temporal distribution of
bfl CTS is undeniable
cognitive and manual designs and
strategies for responses in common
to underlying neurobiological
propensities shared by the early middle
pleistocene Nappers Nappers are people
that actually form and shape these tools
sporadic local enactment by H Heidelberg
heidelbergenis
could well have been responsible for
puzzling exceptional fines what at First
Sight look like impossibly early
instances as Stone working techniques
that flowered only much later on
showing that hand axes could be knapped
with care and detention in Europe before
the middle of the middle pleistocene
thereby disproving a commonly held Butte
to the contrary
the alternative ways of modifying stones
that appeared after 2ma namely on the
one hand to make lcts that's one-sided
and in particular bfl CTS and on the
other two remove usable flakes from
cores
that also may have undergone some
modifications sometimes sort of
facilitate the removal implies that each
erectus could carry out two different
irreversible chains of the manipulative
reduction of stone implying a capacity
for haptic and short-term working memory
long-term memory and perspective memory
respect beyond that of earlier homina or
extant patterns artifact diversity
implies that at times a directors could
recognize not only the irreversibility
of their respective change the
sequential manual reduction Stone but
also their correspondence to distinct
morphological sets which at least is
comparable
to second order cognition that's
understood implicitly by pre-verbal
toddlers nowadays
well-studied Regional differences in the
development of gray matter which may be
prolonged in temporal cortex perhaps
related to its role in integrating
memory
object recognition and other visual
inputs from the perspective of the free
energy principle these differences
testify to structural priors
that inherit from inherit from
epigenetics and contextualized
experience dependent learning and
planning as inference at a somatic time
scale
great and continuing with Snakes and
Ladders
also just to get it set as well the BF
LCT is bi-facially flaked large cutting
tools it's a type of tool
the circumstantial evidence seems to
imply the Adaptive evolution of human
neurobiological propensities that
support prospective memory and Tool
making together with short-term working
memory including haptic working memory
long-term working matter memory and
long-term procedural memory an episodic
memory of past matters and things
these propensities were and are
phylogenetic outcomes of existential
onto genetic programs adapted through
natural selection for satisfying the
bioenergetic requirements of organisms
however teaching and learning Stone
napping skills are very different from a
communicatively challenged H erectus
individual spontaneous enactment
resulting in a disregarded bflct outcome
of iterative inactive haptic lithic
manipulations regardless of any
neurobiologically evolved cognitive
neuronal propensity for such enactments
it's a huge claim
getting and fashioning stone for
subsequent use suggests awareness
a potential albeit delayed advantages
for lessening the efforts needed to
acquire bioenergetic resources
such Behavior draws on short-term and
long-term working memory episodic and
procedural memory and prospective memory
or forethought
to a degree well beyond the capacity of
living anthropoid Apes
those are all the keys for Snakes and
Ladders
there's a strong Relentless even focus
on the
moments of tool production
the cognitive and extended cognitive
phenomena associated with the
performance of that act
specifically with regard to hominids and
with a focus on the BF LCT bifacially
flaked large cutting tool of which the
authors have extensive field expertise
seeing in situ
so Snakes and Ladders uses this fun
board game metaphor to or reference
to explain the sudden appearance and
disappearance not by appeal to a
cultural continuity mechanism
tradition
but rather the instantaneous agential
zone of bounded surprise and action
now just before we get into copy or not
to copy
what I what I think is what we're trying
to do here is hold up the fact that we
believe that these although each each
paper has been discretized to a
particular topic the continuity between
the papers is what we'd really like to
emphasize here because there are such
strong
strands
where basically the shores are within
such easy sight of one another that it's
it's very nice to be able to kind of
float back and forth we're gonna now
focus on the copy or not to copy piece
of this but to
to say that there isn't a way of being
able to look at this as a continuity
um I think we're trying to disrupt that
right now
so try to hold on as much of the stakes
and Ladder key points as you can as we
as we morph into this uh
second perspective it's it's perspective
swapping 101 doesn't mean we're losing
the
um
details of either
want me to start oh yeah I'm on evens
you told me I had to do that okay uh
social learning theories about how
information spreads do not explain how a
seed of information is planted in each
individual brain so we're back to the
brain b stuff
useful lenses the free energy principle
which underpins a generative
hierarchically mechanistic mind or hmm
surprising or uncharacteristic sensory
in physical states are precluded via a
minimization of variation of free energy
interactions involve predictive
processing and consequent perception
action responses active inference yay
actively seeking predicted sensory
exchanges with the world that minimize
surprise or variation of free energy
fundamental involvement of learning
Minds is precisely the mind's I.E the
brains that are concerned
in a mechanistic approach seeking to
ascertain the minimum requirements back
to that threshold thing for an
innovation to Nest as it were in one
individual's Brain before it can do so
and in others
Innovation and innovator are treated
throughout in the context of Habitual
phenotypical behavior of a species from
the perspective
of a con-specific Observer who witnesses
novel or unorthodox Behavior or its
outcome usually through but not
necessarily those that O2 activity
performed by a con specific but which at
the time of the observation have not
been adopted by other con specifics in
the group and therefore have not
undergone social Transmission in many
respects the words are synonymous with
invention and inventor
though these often connote post-hoc
recognition
the imperative to maximize the expected
information
curious Behavior responding to epistemic
affordance resolves uncertainty and
thereby reduces the long-term average of
predictionaries in the future however
this kind of innovative behavior is
risky
owing to its deviation
from those phenotypical responses the
selection is favored in a specific
ecological niche Innovation when viewed
from Charles Darwin's vantage point
of evolution by natural selection may be
a far from advantageous trait deviations
can have under underwear consequences
that even May threaten and innovator's
very survival before reproductive age
can be reached oh the risk Rewards
pre-hawk post-hoc
and that fine line that Bridges the two
continuing with copy or not to copy they
write
and also I will add Dean has
accidentally visually differentiated in
these slides
Innovative Behavior can be regarded as a
latent variable a plausible policy whose
posterior probability must be inferred
from a set of observations
the family of probability densities
entertained by an individual is
restricted to the system's prior
Bayesian beliefs
it can be the case that a con-specific's
Innovative Behavior will not fall neatly
into one of these prior conceptions of a
behavioral policy this means by
definition the Innovative behavior is
both unlikely to be evinced in any given
phenotype and crucially
difficult to recognize when observed by
another
was true for Modern Art was true for the
large tools
small deviations by innovators may be
accommodated by observers who can take
discrepancies into account by making
minor adjustments
an innovator's Behavior
should it diverge markedly from the
repertoire of plausible policies used by
an observer to predict another's
Behavior may be beyond the capacity of
the latter's generative model
a prerequisite of registering and
encoding surprising sites May well be an
ability to modify the generative model
in order to accommodate sensory evidence
that fails to meet top-down predictions
brains might balance top-down
expectations against bottom-up sensory
evidence
the ability to do that dynamically and
to conduct complex computations
suggestive of high attentional executive
control
implies sensitivity to both previous
experience and the current context
perhaps the overriding of top-down
predictions implies that those complex
attentional and strategic components of
working memory
that distinguish
humans from chimpanzees
plausibly familiarity by con specific
observers with the actions demonstrated
in an experiment kept their surprise
associated with the demonstrated actions
within a manageable range and this in
turn prompted copying
and it's easier for chimpanzees to
perform complex actions that are
unorthodox
sorry Jim benzes it's easier for
chimpanzees to perform complex actions
that involve considerable motor demands
than it is for them to reproduce actions
that are unorthodox with regard to their
habitual behavioral repertoire
brains my shoulder
an additional energetic cost whenever a
novel associative Behavior responses are
introduced that may override those
already presents
the acceptability of reproducing a novel
artifact May owe at least as much to the
ways in which broadly similar copies
might be used with predictably accurate
outcomes
again big
serious disciplinary claims also with
Broad transdisciplinary and application
consequences
by focusing attention Less on the
creative process of an innovation more
on The Observers of it
this acceptance of the outcome underpins
its intra and intergenerational
transmission questions raise their head
about does what materialistic phenomena
are implicated as opposed to
psychocognitive and social cognitive
Notions about mental developments during
human evolution
and how and when they impinge on the hmm
of our neogene hominin precursors such
that
only in places seen homo was faithful
copying become widespread and give rise
to technological cumulative complexity
it's obligatory therefore to pay
attention both
to fundamental principles of biological
science with particular reference to
neurobiology and to the evolution of by
natural selection of species of the
genus homo with particular reference to
their brains I added the smiley face
narrowing the range of adult Behavior
opened to him may be protracted
corticogenesis and evolved in homo only
around 0.5 m a
during the Middle pleistocene
in adolescence nowadays co-activity
between prefrontal and caudal cortices
underlies agile working memory
from the perspective of the fep these
differences near anatomical testified
structural priors probably slaves
through neuro-epigenetic Evolution which
contextualize experience dependent
learning
and planning is inference at a somatic
time scale
it's relevant that the interplay between
working memory load and Associated
reinforcement learning affects
prediction errors via from parietal and
dopa energetic striatial
neuronal circuits involving algorithmic
like effects mediated by Loops
with basic Anglia with likely
impingement also of episodic and
procedural long-term memory input
remedial temporal hippocampal cortices
you can read the middle section when
considering early pleistocene Behavior
we need not assume that relations
relationships between different kinds of
memory of memory were less complex
psychocognitively than ours it is
prosaically sufficient to infer that
they were simply less frequent owing to
earlier consolidation of cerebral
networks in Homo erectus smaller brain
that's being restated we already talked
about it earlier in in our introduction
yes it reflects many of the so-called
biological
attributes that archaeologists study in
terms of cranial volume and
developmental trajectories and reaches
towards some of those more ineffable or
at least unrecorded cognitive phenotypes
like working memory ability to integrate
diverse stimuli and so on
more on that
Homo erectus observer's brains may have
locked neuronal networks efficient
enough for enabling them to develop
Innovative behavioral responses in the
early pleistocene that were habit
forming
a zone of bounded surprise or here and
after zbs restricted them
plausibly observations by early Homo
erectus were translated often into
activity intermediate between emulation
and imitation owing to limited foresight
about the significance of precise
manipulations for determining the
practicality and effectiveness of an
outcome dimly invisaged
their zbs limited their ability to join
up the mental steps involved in planning
and to infer a counterfactual
possibilities
that is a fundamental aspect of active
inference
that selection of actions and plans is
based on minimizing the free energy to
be anticipated in undertaking them
minimizing effort
and also extremely interestingly as we
explored in live stream 52 with Lance
DeCosta free energy is not the only
discrepancy measure and one that was
mentioned was the earth movers distance
so it's interesting to think about
active inference with the Earth movers
distance if you're actually moving Earth
zones abounded surprisal zbs are
different from the zones of latent
Solutions zls proposed by Tenny at all
in 2009. in their attempt to explain the
lack of cumulative culture in great apes
on the basis that cultural complexity is
restricted by the Limited potentials for
individual intervention
zones abounded surprisal are separated
by varying degrees of surprisal from the
species's prototypical behavioral
repertoire and could therefore resist
the gravitational pull of the zls
the focus of the zbs concept is on The
Observers and their ability to make
sense of an observed innovation
encoding and subsequent copying of an
innovation depends on the degree of
disparity or surprisal between
predictable behaviors which are those
typical of the species and the
perceptual incoming information about
novel behaviors
the zbs allows any potentially novel or
unorthodox Behavior to be copied
provided that the ranges or levels of
surprisal provoked in observers are
tolerated or manageable by them
the zbs is constrained by the capacity
of a species as cerebral neuronal
Network
as opposed to potentially a
socio-cultural explanation which might
argue that the continuity or pattern
overall of a Tool's appearance would be
rather constrained by the capacity of a
social group's transmission capacity
it's a yes and they're proposing a
different attack
zbs focuses on the Observer of an
innovation and hence zls and zbs can be
useful complementary Concepts I think we
checked but we never went below Min 2 in
this paper
properties of mirror neuron circuitry
are necessary prerequisites for
imitative copying
the left side of our brain contains
neurons with canonical properties
involved in tool use and perhaps
understanding it
the matter of understanding raises
unavoidable awkward epistemological
problems of mirology however virology is
about parts and holes
Cardinal in the ordinal
okay
chimpanzees resemble mccax
and they differ from them
in Sharing what with humans coincident
prefrontal
somatotopic responses to transitive
Behavior intransitive observation
of an action humans differ from both in
that our our
q r q it
I was trying to practice this before we
came on live and I still Trip sorry
argue it
fascic
fasciculate fasciculus white matter has
undergone evolutionary modification
affecting temporal low connectivity
learned behavior involves long-term
working memory and prosecutive memory
conscious modification of learned
behavioral patterns reasonably permits
distinguishing long-term working memory
from short-term attentional working
memories even though most long-term
memory is implicit implicit and
non-declarative the boundary between
explicit and implicit memory is porous
it's a broken mind
still flax implied fact for
propositional perception individual
train sequences change to a greater
extent earlier in learning and stabilize
later
patterns of neural neuronal activity
became increasingly distinct for train
sequences carried out at full speed
The Selective importance of particular
neuronal groups and included striatal
activation comparing the motor sequences
and carried out at different speeds
permitted analysis of the observation
that areas of motor and sensory Motor
cortices Show relatively slight changes
in patterns of neuronal activity that
are specific for particular sequences
following training
possibly on account of the slow speed at
which participants previously been paced
during training hence the finding that
patterns of sequence specific activation
our strongest when performing the
greatest speed implies that
investigating fine-grained patterns of
activity requires participants to cope
with a strong manual challenge
activation is bilateral because
fashioning Stone requires precise and
accurate monitoring in an organized
forward sequence of perception action
with feedback Homer rectus brains had an
appropriate working memory moreover
they had to have a had a hierarchically
organized neurocognitive capacity to
generate in an observer the
combinatorial ability needed for there
to be any acceptably accurate copying
the stone undergoing artifactory
modification as envisaged outcome that
is abstracted
and understood implicitly by both
parties albeit invisible
explicitly during the materializing
through shaping process such
abstractions severely challenges innate
homeostatic drives in naive Observers
cerebral neural Imaging of students
learning to nap chopping tools via V
those learning to nap BF lcts suggests
significant distinctions in their
respective judgments concerning the
physical accuracy of predicted outcomes
versus strategical appropriateness in
preparing the attended tool it is as if
the two groups were trying out different
cognitive strategies differently during
their respective apprenticeships
accurately repeated preparations of BF
lcts evolved hand in hand with
preferential natural selection of a
propensity for developments in haptic
working memory it must not be forgotten
of course that working memory can also
be an external physical resource hashtag
stigmergy that facilitates copying EG
handbooks of instructions
YouTube demonstrations
or physical models available for copying
EG models in an artist studio or stone
artifacts visible to Paleolithic
observers as argued elsewhere working
memory is a complex multi-dimensional
concept
you can take the last part
evolution by natural selection is
inherently conservative
an emergent neural representation is
exploited by by lone individuals need
not have been shared automatically by
other minds and groups largely
inarticulate Homo erectus whose adaptive
priors guided their action perception
Cycles towards adaptive on
surprising states by way of minimizing
variational free energy those priors
could involve neuro epigenetically
controlled expressions of genes
implicated in those cerebral neuronal
developments that prioritize
routine expectations and consolidate
habitual Behavior to the detriment of
recognizing the epistemic affordances
that underwrite Curiosity and surprising
novelty-seeking behavior in consequence
some infrequently found technological
aspects of early pleistocene Innovative
behaviors May well have been isolated
instances until such times active
inference brought about modification of
adaptive Behavior sorry adaptive priors
thereby permitting acceptance
adoption by Observers
of unorthodox behavior that had failed
to provide adaptive advantage hitherto
so much to unpack with what active
inference allows
right
so that is where our discussion of the
key rings of the two papers ends
just as a reminder that more extensive
quotes are great resources to see in the
final versions of the paper and so on
and
in the following couple of slides we
wanted to bring in a few other
directions
a sampling of the
extra resources that Dean and I were
looking through in our DOT zero
preparation
and do you have any comments on this
before I describe
um this side by side
yeah I think it's good that you show the
two representations on the right side of
the screen I I think oftentimes we
think of things of Interstate
as you know here are the two train
tracks and they are in perfect parallel
what I also think often happens is the
shortest distance between two points
from formalism
aspect is a straight line
but when what we're talking about is
generative models we're talking about
two kinds of time one that's continuous
and one that's discrete and
our ability to uptake something may be
afforded when we Meander slightly so the
representation on the left isn't to
remove the idea of the barbell or
to impose on the model that it has to be
direct
sometimes getting to the answer comes
about in kind of strange and wonderful
ways sometimes things happen suddenly
because we Meander so I'll turn over the
actual diagram now to you and be able to
talk about a little bit about that in
terms of how we shape that in terms of
discrete and continuous time
awesome well this is figure 4.3 from par
pazulo and fristence 2022 active
inference textbook that we have textbook
groups at the institute around
and
two different taxonomic groups maybe
generative modulus erectus and
generative modulus habilis or something
like that are juxtaposed in a way that
highlights their structural similarity
but also calls attention to some of
their details on the top is a partially
observable Markov decision process and
this is a discrete time representation
of a generative model
the hidden states are evolving through
time and there's a past present and
future which are indexed with temporal
markers time minus one time right now
time plus one and at each time there's
the emission of observables that's the
tale of two densities it can emit
generative AI densities from hidden
States or it can learn hidden States
from observables that's the a matrix D
is the prior B describes how those
hidden States change through time and G
shapes policy selection through expected
free energy that intervenes in how
hidden States change through time and
more briefly in the continuous time
generative model rather than explicit
representation of past present and
future the approach taken is much more
resonant with generalized coordinates of
motion or a Taylor series expansion
in which
all past present and future time points
are implicitly predicted through the
specification of the derivatives
of increasingly high order around the
target variable latent State X
there's a lot more to say but when I saw
Dean bring in the straight and the wavy
and the kind of meta train track that
together they
enabled seeing
I thought
4.3 that's where we want it to be
and here's the interesting thing
even in that representation if you were
to suddenly realize that you liked
the relaxing Meandering route that
you're not always in a hurry you would
probably have a better chance of
realizing that in continuous time
sadness would occur as you stretched
your your window of analysis out which
again seems counter-intuitive
but that's what the representation
affirms and one last note on this before
you introduce the next one is
in this figure 4.3
we see a crystallization of
methodological pluralism in active
inference so all questions of the form
how does inference active inference
treat X phenomena even for a specified
subsystem there's no a priori reason to
favor the left or the right foot we want
the barbell loaded on both sides before
we bench press it and so even the
decision of the time window and the
treatment of time which is one of the
most absolutely fundamental decisions in
a model let alone further structural
learning questions which were mentioned
earlier in the quotations
even at that most fundamental Divergence
between discrete and continuous time
generative models the active infra ants
absolutely has a decision
so what do you um see here and what do
we want to bring in yeah now this is
this was uh Ryan Smith's paper and what
I what I what I like about this is he
broke it down into decision active
inference just to if you want to go back
and have a look at that live stream set
um
what he was trying to speak to there was
that a lot of stuff going on in folk
psychology doesn't contradict what we
now kind of understand in terms of how
we can model things out using active
inference and again you can you can
explain the diagram better than I can
but I think what's interesting here is
um
to decide to make a choice to copy or
not to copy to
to throw a stone or not to throw a stone
there's two slides here that we kind of
have to kind of pull together again for
for what I wanted to focus on which is
on the next slide next but here
what I want to do is kind of talk about
this paragraph on the bottom left-hand
side
you have a paper about sensory
attenuation what what do we pay
attention to
that's an outcome desensitive
desensitization this only becomes
problematic when contingencies in the
environment when the environment
changes over time
right so we're talking about things that
agents do in in time and in place but
what this paper was talking about was
sort of the folk psychological and some
of those stories that we've used to try
to explain things and focuses on what's
going on in the envelope what's going on
in the niche
this highlights an important distinction
between this type of habit formation and
other mechanisms promoting habit-like
patterns of behavior in decision active
inference for example actions can also
become resistant to change after
repeated experience because agents build
up highly confident beliefs about the
reward probabilities under each action
if contingencies change it can take a
very large number of trials for agents
to unlearn
such be such
beliefs so I wanted to throw this in as
a compliment to the habitization step
that was in the copied or not to copy
paper do you want to explain the diagram
real quick
my only comment there is with respect to
Ali's question about copy discard
the shadow of to copy or not to copy is
to discard or not to discard because if
people have been hitting their rocks one
way and somebody else even if a
functional mirror neurons allow one to
understand that one is doing it
differently
there's a whole variety of things that
can happen and not all of them involve
the successful contagion of even and
resolutely positive Improvement on tool
use and especially with complex
trade-off Frontiers and partially
obscured views and all these other
social complexities
that is going to mean that to copy or
not to copy to discard or not to discard
copy discard becomes a central piece in
compositional accounts of surprise
minimization under the hierarchically
mechanistic minds
so on this slide which was just a
continuation of that live stream
um set per deck I'm going to I'm going
to drop down to the to the fourth
paragraph if the highest value
in an outcome space was specified for
observing tasting ice cream
in the policy and the policy space
included either choose don't move or
choose walk to the ice cream truck and
buy ice cream a deciding active agent
and for active inference agent will
infer that walking to the ice cream
truck and buying ice cream is the
highest probability policy that is it
will form the intention to go buy ice
cream in addition when considering the
range of cases involving goal directed
choice we have been unsuccessful at
identifying examples where the policy
would play a role inconsistent with
represent representing desired outcomes
now here's an interesting thing even
back then
if you look at the ice cream cone and
you ask it
to the third person now Daniel and Dean
looking at the slide is the ice cream
truck closer to us as we're viewing this
or further away from us than the actual
ice cream cone is you get one sense of
it and then if I grab
this line at first it appears that the
ice cream cone truck is closer to us if
I do this however and I grab this line
just like that
pull that away now all of a sudden
what's in the foreground the ice cream
cone so oftentimes when we're trying to
figure out what what we desire or what
our goal is we're completely unaware
of how we're setting up our own frame
what rule we're actually following if we
have a rule
we're completely unaware of it and yet
that has a huge
decision
implication on what's the desired
foreground background here is it it you
know how how are we coming about to this
idea that this this one this one shape
which we're going to have to arrive at
by removing things is more advantageous
than just leaving it the way it is
so just to have one perspective on
something
unidirectional versus to be able to have
those two perspectives on something so
again this was inter in comparison to a
folk psychology telling a folk
psychology Narrative of telling how we
might come to behaving
versus the act of inference what Ryan
wanted to do in this in his paper was
say they're not
think they're not in they're not
fighting with one another
and oftentimes if you actually
understand that you've made a lot of
choices that you're not even aware of
that your generative model sometimes is
a reduction to some rules that you may
or may not even be able to articulate
and that's fine
then yes it will influence what you you
do present as an articulation it doesn't
change the the what we Now understand is
the mechanisms that are present and that
may help us in terms of some of that
predictive process
awesome
live stream 46 way back when
all right just a few more pieces to
bring into the puzzle so I'll give a
first description on each of them and
then Dean feel free to kind of bring in
why you wanted these to be uh here so uh
here's a paper
a variational synthesis of evolutionary
and developmental Dynamics
which was written with Tristan myself
Constance Knight Parr and Campbell
we recently uploaded it to Archive
and
one of the main Novelties or
contributions of this paper was
in contrast with previous multi-scale
biologically oriented active inference
or fep models which use the formalism of
nested pomdps to model nested Markov
blankets thus creating one bigger and
bigger tree with finer and finer leaves
we used a explicit discontinuous
multi-scale or scale friendly jump
such that within the lifetime the
intra-generational action perception
loops and also developmental Loops that
we heard about in some selections from
the papers today
that that particular partition that
thing
over the course of its life in an
ecologically embodied way
can have bottom-up causation to this
higher order thing which is a population
thing and this higher order extended
genotypic thing also uses the exact same
particular partition mathematics and
framing that we see across systems in
actinth and another way to look at that
is here in the center is one thing with
the blue ring going around it at a given
level and it is itself composed of these
smaller things which also are composed
of even smaller things
and also that main blue ring is playing
a role in potentially a larger thing
and this is the scale friendliness or
the scale freeness of the fep formalism
discussed in an ontogenetic phylogenetic
setting within amongst generations and
rather than utilizing this
graft bigger and bigger plmdps strategy
we introduce an explicit discontinuity
in that things at a lower level are
sampled or instantiated from a higher
level distributional thing
and the differential success of those
within generation trajectories
can result in bottom-up causation
modifying the extended genotypic thing
I hope that we'll have more sessions to
talk more about this paper and related
work but just want to give that quick
overview
and I don't have a lot of deep
background in biology so I'm I the
reason why I wanted I was hoping that
you would be interested in at least
touching on this is because I I think
again we're back to so which have we
chosen to do have we chosen to zoom in
on the scale friendly or if we just yes
zoom in on the scale friendly or zoom
out onto the scale three and I think we
get a better understanding when we're
able to
appreciate the differences
and put them back together in our in our
sort of our own model
great on to the next
here is a paper with Sean O'Connor who
led this effort and myself from the end
of 2022 predictive processing
interpretation of the mirror test and
implications of a reflection prediction
for human cognition and just to read one
sentence from the abstract
we hypothesize that a reflection
prediction upon which our predictive
processing interpretation of the mirror
test is built may also offer a novel
perspective to understand how humans
locate themselves relative to a mirror
imitate others and are self-aware from a
social perspective so what have you seen
in that mirror mirror on the screen and
why did you want it here
um because I think the sensory first of
all I strongly recommend people get this
paper and read it because I thought it
was I thought it was an excellent paper
and it should uh it should become on uh
part of more people's reading lists
one of the things that really speaks to
very clearly and makes a strong case
around is the role of sensory
attenuation
and
bringing the the concept of sensory
attenuation into the world of predictive
processing and I think it's would be
something that would be helpful for
people to understand especially if
you're if you're thinking that for
example yeah and I don't forgive Daniel
you'll know what this is but
there was one of the things that was
talked about in this paper was the idea
that if you believe you do not have a
limb
that one of the things that you could do
is come up with a way of a mirror
showing you without that limb even if
you already possessed it so it's going
it's it's reinforcing what
um Hector and Michael and Carl
we're talking about in terms of so how
does how does active inference help us
get to maybe some more plausible answers
in prosaic ways and so the sensory
attenuation piece to me was really
valuable and tied in with some of the
concepts we're talking about here
yeah one thought on that is
let's Grant an effective mirror neuron
or recognition capacity just spatially
in terms of tool usage so that is not
always granted with eyesight and partial
occlusion of the working locations of
tools and all of this but let's just say
that an observer can observe somebody
else doing a motor behavior and entirely
understands the basis of that motor
Behavior like the person does a
pirouette or they write a line in
cursive or they play violin you can have
absolute understanding of the mechanisms
of the baseball pitcher of the hockey
stick
yet
there are multiple Reasons from an
embodied and cognitive perspective why
the behavior cannot be copied we can all
understand that there are certain sport
acts that are not just strength limited
and they're not even necessarily
dexterity Limited
that we cannot do we cannot write in a
language we do not know by hand even
though we might have the motor dexterity
and so that's the semantic
explanation or quite simply and to call
back the zone abounded surprisal
an observer May observe
a heteropraxis a different Praxis
and simply implicitly or even explicitly
believe that's unlikely for me to do
and as it was thought so it shall be
done the Innovation is over
yeah
and then lastly in a little bit
um most extrapolatively
previously in some work
uh I have juxtaposed Buckminster
Fuller's life and work and times with
that of William Blake and the prompting
quote from the paper was above zones
abounded surprisal are different from
the zones of latent solution
in their attempt to explain the lack of
cumulative culture and great apes on the
basis that cultural complexity is
restricted by the Limited potentials for
individual invention
so
Bucky and Blake were both tremendously
inventive individuals and
to reflect a few lines of some Blake
poetry
the augeries of Innocence begins with to
see a world in a grain of sand and a
whole and a heaven in a wildflower hold
Infinity in the palm of your hand and
Eternity in an hour
those are some of the famous opening
lines of that poem and they speak to
this time
representation
but the closing lines are less often
quoted
when we uh we are led to believe a lie
when we see not through the eye which
was born in a night to perish in a night
when the soul slept in beams of light
God Appears and God is light to those
poor souls who dwell in night
but does a human form display
to those who dwell in Realms of day
and I'll let you get the word on that
well here's the thing I want to thank
again the authors who are going to be
joining us for the dot one and Dot two
for allowing us
to
pull two of their papers into proximity
and allow us to talk about them so
proximally because we I think I speak
for both of us but you can correct me on
this Daniel I think with the use of
active inference
um and our con our continuous updating
with active inference as as a way of
strategizing are coming to realize that
sometimes things that seem really distal
and unrelated when brought together
you as the person who is looking at two
things at once with both of your eyes
open
um
tend to learn a lot and so whether it's
pulling Buck Mr Fuller and Blake into
the into the same slide deck or talking
about to copy or not to copy and Snakes
and Ladders it's it's actually a real
treat
to be able to bring things that seem
like well that that no you know
conventionally that was field work and
this is lab work being able to have one
foot in both of those Realms really
helps the person who who likes to go
back and forth who is moving from a
position of being really familiar with
the subject matter to being somebody who
can actually get into the predictive
matter matters
because they're more comfortable in
doing the update thing
they're not quite so stuck and bound so
and that and that means when I see zls
and zbs beside one another
makes me very very happy so that's
that's my
that's why I wanted the I wanted you to
get acknowledged for some of the work
that you've done in terms of this isn't
the first time that you've seen an
advantage in bringing two things that
don't seem like they belong on the same
table and bringing them together and
kind of going whoa
look what happens when you do
great thanks any final comments or I'll
give a final thought
go for it all right well I would just
like to Echo
uh
your words we really appreciated even
dare I say working with the authors in
this dot zero and even negative dot one
the first of its kind
interval
these papers
initially
to me at least felt like two
pillowy beds of plain text
can't think of any other way to say it
right now
however once we dug at that field site
and we brushed off some of those uni and
bifacial tools and ideas there was just
more and more to find than explore
so I'm very much looking forward to the
coming dot 1.2 and potentially Beyond
and we hope you've enjoyed this 53.0
thanks Daniel all right thank you Dean
farewell